Finding aid for the Yoshie Yoshida Papers LSC.2350
UCLA Library Special Collections
Yoshie Yoshida papers
1959-2005
UCLA Library Special Collections
Yoshida, Yoshie
LSC.2350
2.6 Linear Feet (9 boxes)
As an art critic and curator, Yoshie Yoshida (1929-2016) organized many exhibitions and events in Japan. After becoming a member of Art Critics Association, he was also engaged in supporting political and performance art. The collection ranges from monographs, serials and audiovisual material to scrapbooks, article clippings, exhibition programs, posters and correspondence.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
CONTAINS AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS: This collection contains processed audiovisual materials. All requests to access digital materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Source of Acquisition
The acquisition was through the gift of the Yoshida family, with the assistance of Yoshiko Shimada (who compiled the archival materials into files) and William Marotti, in 2016. The "Kazuko Tsujimura" folder was donated by Tsujimura's brother to Yoshiko Shimada and added to the collection in 2017.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9983164053606533
Biography/History
Yoshie Yoshida, an art critic, curator, and event/exhibition organizer, was born in Japan in 1929. In the 1950s he carried Matsuki's Hiroshima Panels throughout Japan as a travelling exhibit. Upon publishing a book "Takiguchi Shuzo oboegaki" in 1961, he became a member of Art Critics Association. In 1965, he founded an artist-run gallery, Modern Art Center of Japan. Yoshida organized an art performance, Haisen Bansankai (Dinner Party Commemorating WWII Defeat, 1962) and Festival of Humans and Earth (1970). He also supported political art such as Akasegawa Genpei's 1000-yen Trial (1965-67) and anti-expo art movement (1969). He died in Tokyo, Japan, in 2016. Among his works are "Kaitaigeki no maku orite: 60-nendai zen'ei bijutsushi" (avant-garde art history in the 60s) in 1982, and "Matsuzawa Yutaka Pusai no hako" (1983) where Yoshida edited the portfolio of the artist.
Scope and Content
This collection was created by an art critic Yoshie Yoshida (1929-2016), and ranges from monographs, serials and audiovisual material to scrapbooks, article clippings, exhibition programs, posters and correspondence. Monographs center on exhibition catalogs, materials on surrealism, and books by/on particular artists (Shuzo Takiguchi, Genpei Akasegawa and Yutaka Matsuzawa). Serials chiefly consist of newsletters from art museums and institutes. An extensive amount of materials and documents are also found on Butoh (a Japanese avant-garde dance form). Other materials and documents cover social, political as well as artistic events/movements in which Yoshida was involved, such as Ningen to Daichi no Matsuri (Festival of Humans and Earth), Sanrizuka Struggle and Artist Union.
Art critics -- Japan -- Archives.; Arts, Japanese -- 20th century -- Archives.; Yoshida, Yoshie
- Scrapbook 1, 1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Scrapbook 2, 1965-1968 (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
- Scrapbook 3, 1969-1971 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Scrapbook 4, 1971-1976 (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
- Scrapbook 5, 1977-1979 (Box 1, Folder 7, Box 2, Folder 1)
- Scrapbook 6, 1979-1981 (Box 2, Folder 2-3)
- Scrapbook 7, 1981-1983 (Box 2, Folder 4-5)
- Scrapbook 8, 1983-1987 (Box 2, Folder 6-7)
- Scrapbook 9, 1988-2005 (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
- Articles and exhibition programs, 1963-1970 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  Scope and Content
  Includes Anti-Expo statements by Yoshida and items on Modern Art Center of Japan.
- Court documents, 1963-1972 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  Includes documents on 1000-yen Note Trial and Utopia and Visions Exhibition Q&A.
- Artist Union, 1975-1979 (Box 3, Folder 5-6)
  Articles from "Artist Union" newsletters, articles on Artist Union, and programs of Artist Union Symposiums.
- Sanrizuka, 1978-1982 (Box 3, Folder 7-8)
  Flyers for assemblies, articles and newsletters relating Sanrizuka Struggle (a series of protests against the construction of Narita Airport in Tokyo). Includes items on Issaku Tomura (Protest Coalition leader) Exhibition, curated by Yoshida.
- Cosmos Exhibition, 1973-1974 (Box 4, Folder 1-4)
  Articles, flyers and correspondence on Cosmos Exhibition held in Sao Paulo in 1974. Files composed by Yoshida. Includes Yoshida's journals during the exhibition and Brazilian trip.
- Festival of Humans and Earth (File 1), 1971 (Box 4, Folder 5-7)
  Photographs, correspondence, programs, articles relating to the event organized by Yoshida. Contains documentation on the event.
- Festival of Humans and Earth (File 2), 1971 (Box 4, Folder 8, Box 5, Folder 1)
  This file has "Ozaki" (event co-organizer) written on cover, and centers on correspondence and mail art.
- Correspondence, 1978-2003 (Box 5, Folder 2-4)
  Chiefly letters and postcards from artists.
- International Surrealism Exhibition, 1975-1978 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  Articles, flyers and program on the Exhibition held in Chicago, 1978, organized by Yoshida.
- War-related materials, 1975-1978 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  A military artist directory and articles on war/military art.
- Butoh, 1977-2001 (Box 6, Folder 1-2, Box 5, Folder 7-8)
  Programs, flyers and newsletters related to Butoh (Japanese avant-garde dance form). Contains letters from Yoko Ashikawa (Tatsumi Hijikata's student and collaborator).
- Shuzo Takiguchi, 1970-1979 (Box 6, Folder 3-4)
  Photos, books and correspondence. Includes Liberty Passport from Takiguchi and photos by Mitsutoshi Hanaga.
- Zuisoroku by Hironae Yoshida, 1945-1946 (Box 6, Folder 5-7)
  Photocopy of a three-volume autobiography written by Hironae Yoshida (Yoshida's father).
- Kazuko Tsujimura, 1965-1978 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  Collection of Yoshida's portraits and correspondence with Yoshida, collected by Kazuko Tsujimura.
- Audiovisual materials, 1990-1998 (Box 7)
  Ten VHS tapes, including Nobuyuki Oura's "Enkin o kakaete," Butoh performances, and videos featuring Isao Mizutani and Takami Sakurai.
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  COLLECTION CONTAINS AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS: Audiovisual materials in this collection will require assessment and possible digitization for safe access. All requests to access special collections material must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
- Posters, 1963-1976 (Box 8)
  Posters and photographs for exhibitions and events, including 1000-yen Note Trial 1965 Matsuzawa Yutaka "Pusai no itai ni tsuite" 1964 Photographs for the Festival of Humans and Earth posters 1971 Global Art Vision 1971 Urban Open Space in Hiroshima 1972 Hi-red Center 1966?
- Yutaka Matsuzawa, 1951-1973 (Box 9, Folder 1-4)
  Postcards, flyers and programs for exhibitions and events organized by Yutaka Matsuzawa. Also includes correspondence from Matsuzawa to Yoshida. Two issues of "Art & Project bulletin" are in English.